{"tossups": [{"question": "The Wei Zhi puts this place 12,000 li north of a place called Dog Slave Country. Xu Fu likely visited this place in his search for the elixir of life and may have claimed one of its mountains to be Mt. Penglai. Red paint used to depict tattooing on haniwa statues is evidence for the claim that some of the people of this place were descendants of Wu Taibo of the Spring and Autumn State of Wu. People from this place were the most distant of the Dongyi. An early exonym for this place may have etymological ties to a word for \u201cbent down\u201d or (*) \u201cdwarf\u201d. Chinese sources describe a civil war in this place that ended with the accession of a sorcerer queen who only communicated through her brother. The first recorded name for this place is wa or wo and the state of Yamataikoku here was ruled by Queen Himiko. For 10 points, identify this island nation to the east of China known locally as Nihon or Nippon.", "answer": "Japan (accept Wa, Wo, Nippon, or Nihon before mentioned and any island in the archipelago)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Japan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Japan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Wa, Wo, Nippon, or Nihon before mentioned and any island in the archipelago"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s mother Beatrice married Godfrey the Bearded of Lorraine to provide military support during her son\u2019s minority, but the Holy Roman Emperor imprisoned Beatrice and her son Frederick because Godfrey was his enemy. This leader\u2019s husband Godfrey the Hunchback was assassinated in Flanders while taking a crap five years after she had left him. The animosity between this woman and her nephew Godfrey of Bouillon kept her from participating in the First Crusade. This woman\u2019s greatest enemy walked through the Mont Cenis Pass barefoot and wearing a hair shirt so as to not be excommunicated by (*) Pope Gregory VII. For 10 points, name this northern Italian badass woman of the 12th century who made Henry IV stand in the snow outside her castle as a defender of the Papacy.", "answer": "Matilda of Tuscany (or Matilda of Canossa)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Matilda of Tuscany</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Matilda of Tuscany"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Matilda of Canossa"}, {"question": "Before one battle this man led, all the commanders on his side reluctantly agreed to the orders delivered by Cornelis de Witt despite agreeing with them so that they could appear to be blameless if the battle went poorly. This commander declared war on the Isles of Scilly and peace was not declared until 1986, well after this man\u2019s death. While captain of the Salamander, this leader gained fame for freeing Christian slaves in North Africa. He became friends with Frederick III of Denmark after relieving a Swedish siege of Danzig without fighting. This leader reversed the gains of Robert Holmes in West Africa and defeated (*) George Monck at the protracted Four Days\u2019 Battle. As titular commander, this man led the forces who captured the HMS Royal Charles during the Raid on the Medway. For 10 points, name this Dutch admiral during the Anglo-Dutch Wars.", "answer": "Michiel de Ruyter", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Michiel de Ruyter</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Michiel de Ruyter"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable One of the first attempts at accomplishing this goal was carried out through three letters including Viam agnoscere veritatis and Dei patris immensa. A voyage by Sempad the Constable was used to promote this goal by his brother Hethum I, king of Cilician Armenia. Plans for achieving this goal drawn up at the Second Council of Lyons fell through due to a lack of royal support. This goal was rendered obsolete by the Treaty of Aleppo. The defeat of the Principality of Antioch was delayed by roughly five years because it had accomplished this goal to fight (*) Sultan Baibars. Louis IX received only a demand for submission after sending William of Rubruck to Karakorum to facilitate this goal. For 10 points, identify this informal and never fully realized diplomatic situation in which the descendants of Genghis Khan allied with the Franks against the Muslim world.", "answer": "European-Mongol alliance against the Mamluks (accept Franco-Mongol alliance before \u201cFranks\u201d; accept answers conveying a political and/or military alliance being made between a European power and a Mongol khanate; prompt on Christian-Mongol alliance)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>European-Mongol alliance against the Mamluks</u></b>", "acceptable": ["European-Mongol alliance against the Mamluks"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Franco-Mongol alliance before \u201cFranks\u201d; accept answers conveying a political and/or military alliance being made between a European power and a Mongol khanate; prompt on Christian-Mongol alliance"}, {"question": "Local rulers frequently paid the voluntary tuition of poor students at a university in this city because not doing so would be too damaging to their reputation. The Heliodorus Pillar was erected by an ambassador representing the ruler of this city. This city was only known from literary sources until Alexander Cunningham began excavating it at Saraikhala. This city was connected to the city of Tamralipta by the Uttarapatha, or \u201cnorthern road\u201d. A ruler of this city named \u0100mbhi was the bitter enemy of (*) King Porus and contributed 5000 men to the Macedonian army at the Battle of Hydaspes. This city is most famous for the university that supported the Ayurvedic scholar Charaka and the Sanskrit grammarian P\u0101\u1e47ini. For 10 points, identify this city in the Punjab home to an early university where Kautilya wrote the Artha\u015b\u0101stra (\u201car-ta-shah-stra\u201d).", "answer": "Taxila or Tak\u1e63a\u015bil\u0101 (\u201ctuck-shuh-shih-lah\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Taxila or Tak\u1e63a\u015bil\u0101</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Taxila or Tak\u1e63a\u015bil\u0101"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "\u201ctuck-shuh-shih-lah\u201d"}, {"question": "A speech delivered at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in 1967 was influential in the formulation of this program. Four tests of the HOE system were done on Kwajalein to gauge the efficacy of this project. This program was criticized for upsetting the geopolitical balance at the (*) Reykjavik Summit. One part of this endeavor envisioned using tungsten kinetic missiles in a system called Brilliant Pebbles. This program was publicly announced fifteen days after the \u201cEvil Empire\u201d speech and sought to replace the policy of mutually assured destruction. For 10 points, name this proposed missile protective measure first proposed in 1983 and nicknamed \u201cStar Wars\u201d.", "answer": "Strategic Defense Initiative (accept Star Wars before mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Strategic Defense Initiative</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Strategic Defense Initiative"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Star Wars before mentioned"}, {"question": "During the Athenian Skirophoria festival, white versions of these objects were carried from the Acropolis to Phalerum. In 1710, Jean Marius opened the first shop for these items in Europe and received a five year monopoly on their sale. Robinson Crusoe creates one of these objects modeled off of one he sees in Brazil, leading some of these objects to be called \u201cRobinsons\u201d in England. One of these things appears with two crossed keys on the coat of arms for the sede vacante (*) Holy See. The Real Cherbourg created an armored one of these objects to protect Nicolas Sarkozy and the 2014 Hong Kong riots were named after these items. For 10 points, Georgi Markov was injected with ricin via what kind of object, usually carried to protect one from the sun or the rain?", "answer": "umbrella (accept parasol)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>umbrella</u></b>", "acceptable": ["umbrella"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept parasol"}, {"question": "The first known laws regulating this commodity were issued by Domitian in 92 CE because too much was being produced. The work of the Carthaginian writer Mago contains the first mention of the passum type of this substance. A famous variety of this commodity from Kos was treated with sea water and lower-quality varieties of this good were sometimes processed in fumaria. The Greeks called southern Italy (*) Oenostria in reference to its production of this good and also pioneered a preparation technique now known as pigeage. A bottle found at Speyer, Germany contains the oldest surviving example of this good, dating from around 320 CE, and is likely still drinkable. For 10 points, name this good, the preferred drink of Dionysus.", "answer": "wine", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>wine</u></b>", "acceptable": ["wine"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A statue of Jesus on the cross with huge eyes is the first shot in Julien Bryan\u2019s filming of this event. This event took place in the Institute of Archaeology because of its small and dark rooms. This event was followed by a similar event the next year that was advertised with posters featuring a racist caricature of the title character of the opera Jonny Plays. The works displayed at this event were intentionally hung haphazardly and without frames, and much of the remaining wall space was used for (*) defamatory slogans. This event was claimed to contain \u201ceffigies of wickedness\u201d by its organizer Adolf Ziegler and featured works by artists such as Emil Nolde, Oskar Kokoschka, and Paul Klee. For 10 points, identify this 1937 event in Munich which showed art deemed counter to the ideals of the Nazi Party.", "answer": "Degenerate Art Exhibition(accept Entartete Kunst Ausstellung)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Degenerate Art Exhibition</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Degenerate Art Exhibition"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Entartete Kunst Ausstellung"}, {"question": "This kingdom once allied with a queen who, during a negotiation with the Portuguese, sat on a servant when not offered a chair, and then killed the servant after standing, saying that she \u201cnever sat on the same chair twice\u201d. A prince of this kingdom named Henrique was appointed bishop of Utica and died en route to the Council of Trent. A woman who claimed to be possessed by St. Anthony of Padua and to meet with God weekly led the Antonian Movement during a civil war in this kingdom. \u00c1lvaro I of this kingdom renamed his capital S\u00e3o Salvador and introduced European titles for nobles. (*) King Nzinga a Nkuwu was the first ruler of this kingdom to convert to Christianity, which had been brought to the area first by Diogo C\u00e3o. For 10 points, name this kingdom of west-central Africa, the namesake of a river and two modern countries with capitals at Brazzaville and Kinshasa.", "answer": "Kingdom of Kongo", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kingdom of Kongo</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kingdom of Kongo"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The most famous person to have worked on determining this quantity had earlier invented the grasshopper escapement and the gridiron pendulum, both important for advancing the measurement of this quantity. Johannes Werner was the first to propose the lunar distance method of calculating this quantity. Several acts of Parliament named for this quantity in the 18th century encouraged the development of a means of calculating this quantity with (*) rewards now equal to over \u00a31 million today. Dead reckoning was the primary means of determining this quantity until the invention of the marine chronometer by John Harrison, which allowed one\u2019s position on the globe to be accurately calculated. For 10 points, this is what quantity describing one\u2019s east-west position relative to the Prime Meridian?", "answer": "longitude (accept time before \u201clunar distance\u201d and prompt after)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>longitude</u></b>", "acceptable": ["longitude"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept time before \u201clunar distance\u201d and prompt after"}, {"question": "On an expedition led by this man, he trampled a British flag flown by a Native American chief, winning the concession of the land on which Fort Brady would be built. In a cartoon, this man says that prefers \u201clong shots\u201d because they allow for more \u201cexercise of skill and ingenuity\u201d as a fox escapes with a turkey. This man represented the US during the negotiation of the Treaty of Fort Meigs. The aforementioned expedition mislabeled Red Cedar Lake as the source of the (*) Mississippi River. As Secretary of War, this man carried out the Indian Removal Act. This man\u2019s bid for the presidency with William Orlando Butler in 1848 split the Democratic Party and led to Zachary Taylor\u2019s victory. For 10 points, name this early 19th century Michigan politician.", "answer": "Lewis Cass", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Lewis Cass</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Lewis Cass"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One ruler of this city took his name from a mythical man-eating dog that lives underwater. The most famous ruler of this city had two zoos in his palace, one for birds of prey and the other for all other animals, that together employed over 300 people. This city constructed a levee named for an allied ruler that split the freshwater and saltwater sections of a nearby lake. This city was settled shortly after its founders were exiled for sacrificing the daughter of the leader of (*) Culhuacan and wearing her flayed skin. This city was divided into 4 sections called campans, and each campan was further split into 20 calpulli. The Hueyi Tzompantli (\u201cWAY-yee tsohm-PAHN-tlee\u201d), or \u201cGreat Skull Rack\u201d, of this city was estimated to contain 60,000 skulls from sacrificial victims, many of whom were probably killed on the Templo Mayor. Taken by the Spanish under Hern\u00e1n Cort\u00e9s, this is, for 10 points, what capital city of the Aztec Empire?", "answer": "Tenochtitlan", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tenochtitlan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tenochtitlan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The city of Toulon was emptied of most of its population while this force peacefully occupied it for eight months. A map created by this force claims to have used Columbus\u2019 now lost maps as a source and its notable depiction of Antarctica probably does not represent actual knowledge of the continent. This force brought the craft of cannon-making to the Sultanate of Aceh to attempt to contain Portuguese influence in the Indian Ocean and many of the cannons it brought there were later melted to make Dutch church bells. John Elphinstone was one of the commanders who defeated this force at the Battle of (*) \u00c7e\u015fme. This force constructed the ship Mahmudiye, the largest warship of its time, in part to raise morale after its defeat at Navarino. For 10 points, identify this force that was most famously defeated at Lepanto.", "answer": "Ottoman navy (prompt on less specific answers referencing the Ottomans/their military)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ottoman navy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ottoman navy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on less specific answers referencing the Ottomans/their military"}, {"question": "Within a larger level in an N64 game, the player must rescue Chris P. Bacon from a temple in this place. The language of this place is claimed to be the ancestor of all modern languages in a 2001 film, somehow allowing its residents to speak English and French. This place is unwittingly discovered when Hans tackles Count Saknussemm for eating his pet duck in the 1959 film version of (*) Journey to the Center of the Earth. In a cartoon, this place has an ice cream-shooting tank in its arsenal, is reached by the protagonist in a vehicle that runs on \u201csong fuel\u201d, and has the world\u2019s oldest bubble. In Age of Mythology, the battle between Gargarensis and Arkantos destroys this island and its advanced civilization. For 10 points, identify this sunken city of Greek legend.", "answer": "Atlantis", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Atlantis</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Atlantis"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One account of a ruler of this kingdom claims that he took power after assassinating King Candaules after falling in love with Candaules\u2019 to-be wife Tudo. The capital of this kingdom supposedly lay on a stream with golden sand and was one of the earliest places to separate the components of electrum. One ruler of this kingdom chose to patronize the Oracle of Delphi because it correctly predicted that he was eating lamb and turtle 100 days after he dispatched his envoys to visit it. This kingdom\u2019s first king of the Atyad Dynasty, Manes, is the origin for one of this kingdom\u2019s alternate names, Maeonia. Under Alyattes II, this kingdom\u2019s war with the (*) Medes was called off due to a solar eclipse. This kingdom produced the world\u2019s first known coins. For 10 points, what was this wealthy Anatolian kingdom ruled from Sardis by Croesus?", "answer": "Lydia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Lydia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Lydia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A member of this group and one-time gang leader was once attacked by a band of robbers, but was able to convince them to convert to his faith by beating the snot out of them. The face of one member of this group supposedly could glow in the dark because he had so much grace and he wrote 50 Spiritual Homilies. This group developed the tradition of hesychasm, or experiencing God through (*) silent prayer and living a solitary life. The most famous of this group was supposedly beaten by demons while living as a hermit in a tomb, after which he formed the first Christian monastery out of his many followers. Including St. Moses the Black and Macarius the Great, for 10 points, identify this influential group of early Christians who lived in Egypt and initiated the monastic movement, most famously represented by St. Anthony.", "answer": "Desert Fathers (prompt on Eremites, hermits, ascetics, or monks)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Desert Fathers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Desert Fathers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Eremites, hermits, ascetics, or monks"}, {"question": "In 1869, Rear Admiral Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov erected a wooden cross to commemorate this event. Prior to this battle, one side tried to drag its ships over the Hanko Peninsula on ox skins. The turning point of this engagement was the capture of the ship Tranan, creating a hole in one side\u2019s defensive line. At the end of this battle, Nils Ehrenskj\u00f6ld was taken prisoner aboard his flagship, the pram Elefanten, which was claimed by the winning side to be a frigate to increase their glory. (*) 6 years to the day after this battle, the 1720 Battle of Grengam between the same navies marked the end of Swedish supremacy in the Baltic. For 10 points, identify this 1714 naval battle of the Great Northern War, the first major victory for the Russian Navy.", "answer": "Battle of Gangut (accept names that sound pretty similar, there are many similar sounding names)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Gangut</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Gangut"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept names that sound pretty similar, there are many similar sounding names"}, {"question": "The founder of this kingdom took power by convincing an invading Mongol army that he was a deposed king and that he would hand over the kingdom to them if they ousted the current king, but he destroyed the Mongols as they celebrated their victory over his enemy. The Paregreg was a civil war fought between the \u201ceastern court\u201d and the \u201cwestern court\u201d of this kingdom and was won by Wikramawardhana. This polity killed the Sundanese royal family at the Battle of Bubat when they refused the demeaning marriage terms offered by the minister (*) Gajah Mada. The voyages of Zheng He brought the first significant populations of Muslims to this polity. This kingdom\u2019s name refers to a bitter fruit and was at its most powerful under Hayam Wuruk. For 10 points, identify this Hindu kingdom established by Raden Wijaya on Java.", "answer": "Majapahit Kingdom/Empire", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Majapahit Kingdom/Empire</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Majapahit Kingdom/Empire"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The town of Cupids was an early British settlement in this modern country and was founded the generically-named John Guy. Due to an early Portuguese explorer of the coast of this modern country, one of its northeastern provinces is named after the Portuguese word for \u201cfarmer\u201d. The site of Santa Cruz de Nuca on the west coast was the only Spanish settlement in this country. Father Le Loutre\u2019s War was fought between English and French (*) settlers in this country. York Factory was an early economic center for this country in Rupert\u2019s Land. An eastern peninsula of this country derives its name from its brief Scottish colonization. For 10 points, name this modern country whose first settlement by Europeans was by the Norse around 1000 CE in Newfoundland.", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}